John and Ginny Dildine collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Sound Recordings
  - AFC 1975/001: SR071, Recorded: ca. 1963, RXG 0750; 28:57
    11:01 Dildine introduces the next song, "Bullgine Run." It is not on the tape.
    11:29 Collins and Dildine talk about the previous song.
    11:47 Dildine asks Collins how she approaches traditional material of this sort. Collins responds.
    13:45 Dildine talks about Mike Seeger and how some people sing folk music as if they were popular songs (e.g., juke box songs). He and Collins discuss this.
    17:28 Collins says that she is not a traditional folk singer. She talks about contemporary songs. Collins and Dildine talk about singers being "socially aware" of what's going on around them.
    18:53 Dildine does a station break. Dildine and Collins talk about the next song, "Hey Nelly Nelly."
    20:30 The song is not on the tape. Collins talks about the "point" of the album Judy Collins #3.
    23:30 Dildine and Collins talk about "old bad songs" and "new bad songs." Collins talks about her "pet theory" about folk music.
    24:48 Collin talks about her life as a performer and how it affects her music.
    26:47 Dildine and Collins introduce the next song, ‘The Dove." It is not on the tape. [End of the Collins interview.]
    27:22 Dildine talks about an album called "Mountain Music Played on the Autoharp." He closes the broadcast.
  - AFC 1975/001: SR072, Recorded: 1963-08-25, RXG 0751; 30:02
    This is a recording for a Dildine radio broadcast. He has a live guest, Tossi Aaron.
    Start Dildine and Aaron talk about a number of things including: folk songs, riddles and jokes (she tells several); children's songs and games; hootenannies; and the 2nd Annual Philadelphia Folk Festival. Aaron introduces the next song.
    9:00 "Fernacio" Aaron
    11:50 Dildine and Aaron talk about a song called "Butcher Boy" and unaccompanied singing. Aaron introduces the next song.
    13:30 "Walie Walie" Aaron
    16:20 Dildine and Aaron talk about "the spell cast" by the previous song and the mood set by quiet songs. They talk about how to reach people through singing. They talk about her records and making recordings. Aaron introduces the next song.
    25:58 "Every Night when the Sun Goes Down" Aaron
    29:31 Dildine thanks Aaron and closes the broadcast.
    30:02 End
  - AFC 1975/001: SR073, Recorded: 1963-12-15, RXG 0752; 34:02
    This is a recording of a Dildine radio broadcast. He has a live guest, Mike Seeger. They are going to attempt to define bluegrass music and will discuss its evolution using a tape of a number of recordings that Seeger has prepared. This is the first of two parts of this program. The second is SR074.
    Start Dildine introduces Mike Seeger. They have a tape, which Seeger made several years ago, with examples of bluegrass music's evolution. Seeger fits bluegrass into the genre of country music. He discusses Bill Monroe and the Bluegrass Boys. Seeger talks about old time music. He introduces the first (recorded) song.
    4:49 "Barbara Allen" J.N. Marler, a capella, from a 1938 Library of Congress field recording
    5:53 Seeger discusses the previous song. Seeger relates ballad singing to Bill Monroe and bluegrass music.
    7:22 Sally Goodin" recorded 1922 A.C. ["Eck"] Robertson, fiddle
    10:22 Seeger discusses the previous song and the fiddler. He discusses how the banjo came into country music. He introduces the next song.
    12:12 "Darlin' Cora" [also known as "Darling Corey"] B.F. Shelton, banjo and vocal
    16:00 Seeger discusses the banjo and the fiddle coming together to be the beginnings of string band music. He introduces the next song.
    16:43 "Whoop the Devil Round," Library of Congress recording in the 1930's the musicians are not identified
    18:15 Seeger discusses the previous song. He talks about when the guitar came into mountain and country music, as did the autoharp and mandolin. He introduces the next song.
    19:50 "Old Joe Clark" recorded in the mid 1929s Ernest V. Stoneman and His Dixie Mountaineers
    23:01 Seeger discusses the previous song. He introduces the next song.
    23:35 "Riding on the Train 45" Wade Mainer, Zeke Morris and Steve Ledford (fiddle)
    24:45 Seeger discusses the previous song. Dildine does a station break. Seeger discusses the growth of country music and country recordings. He introduces the next song.
    26:38 "Who's That Knocking" The Carter Family
    29:38 Dildine points out that the previous song is the first example (of the songs played) where the guitar takes a break (i.e., a solo). Seeger says that it was played by Maybelle Carter. They discuss the previous song. Seeger talks about the Monroe brothers. He introduces the next song.
    31:35 "Darling Corey" The Monroe Brothers
    34:01 End
  - AFC 1975/001: SR074, Recorded: 1963-12-15, RXG 0753; 34:02
    This is a recording of a Dildine radio broadcast. He has a live guest, Mike Seeger. They are going to attempt to define bluegrass music and will discuss its evolution using a tape of a number of recordings that Seeger has prepared. This is the second of two parts of this program. The first is SR073.
    Start Dildine and Seeger discuss the previous song. Dildine points out that this is the first song on which the mandolin is played. Seeger says that the performer was Bill Monroe. They discuss the two recordings of "Darling Corey." They discuss the impact of the radio on the music. Seeger introduces the next song.
    2:20 "Have a Feast Tonight" Monroe Brothers
    4:30 Seeger discusses the previous song. He says that all of the previous songs can be called "old time music" but not [yet] bluegrass music. Dildine and Seeger talk about the mandolin and Bill Monroe. They talk about the evolution of the music in the 1930s. Seeger says that bluegrass music takes in its current form in 1945 when Lester Flatt and Earl Scruggs joined Bill Monroe.
    11:49 "Molly and Tenbrooks" Monroe, Flatt and Scruggs
    14:28 Seeger discusses the previous song then introduces the next song.
    15:03 "Toy Heart" Monroe, Flatt, Scruggs and Chubby Wise
    17:43 Seeger and Dildine discuss the previous song. Seeger discusses the musical form(s) of bluegrass music. He introduces the next song.
    19:05 "Drunkard's Hell" The Stanley Brothers
    21:35 Seeger discusses the previous song. He discusses improvisation and then introduces the next song.
    22:05 "Rawhide" Bill Monroe and the Bluegrass Boys, instrumental
    24:33 Seeger introduces the next song. It is extracts from three versions of the same song, from oldest to newest.
    25:30 "Down in the Willow Garden" Texas Gladden (vocal) and Hobart smith (fiddle); Wade Mainer; Osborne Brothers
    27:58 Dildine and Seeger close the broadcast.
    29:12 End
  - AFC 1975/001: SR075, Recorded: 1964-02-18, RXG 0754; 28:57
    This seems to be a recording of portion of a performance by Mississippi John Hurt and Reverend Robert Wilkins at the Ontario Place in Washington, D.C. The recording quality is poor and the song lyrics are difficult to understand. See SR076 for an interview of Reverend Wilkins by John Dildine.
    Start [unidentified song] Hurt
    4:28 "No Body's Business" Hurt
    7:37 [movement on stage, guitar tuning, etc.]
    9:55 [Do Lord, Remember Me] Wilkins
    13:45 ["Rock of Ages, Hear from Me"] [The guitar accompaniment is the same as "This Land is your Land."] Wilkins
    18:44 [audience noise, guitar tuning]
    20:10 ["Highway to Heaven"] Wilkins
    22:40 [unidentified] Wilkins
    25:00 [guitar tuning and unintelligible talking]
    26:23 "Just a Closer Walk with Thee" Wilkins
    28:57 End
  - AFC 1975/001: SR076 (1), Recorded: 1964-02-18, RXG 0755; 25:52
    The first portion of this tape is an interview of Reverend Robert Wilkins by John Dildine. It was made at the Ontario Place in Washington D.C. on February 18, 1964. See SR075 for part of the performance by Reverend Wilkins. The second portion of this tape is a recording of part of a U.S. Senate hearing and is not related to the Dildine collection.
    Start Dildine introduces this recording.
    1:12 Dildine interviews the Reverend Robert Wilkins. Among the subject discussed are: Wilkins recordings; Wilkins no longer singing blues and singing only sacred music; Wilkins background and history; how he learned to play guitar; his military service in WWI; his faith; his church; and bringing his music to the public.
    16:45 End of interview.
  - AFC 1975/001: SR076 (2), Recorded: unknown, RXG 0755; 8:30
    This is a recording of a Dildine radio broadcast. He plays some Irish recordings.
  - AFC 1975/001: SR077, Recorded: 1964-02-23, RXG 0756; 39:57
    This is a recording for a John Dildine radio broadcast with The New Lost City Ramblers as live guests. The band is composed of Mike Seeger, John Cohen and Tracy Schwartz.
    Start Dildine says he is going to play a recording of The NLCR.
    0:10 unidentified instrumental The NLCR
    1:20 Dildine talks with Mike Seeger about what the band is currently playing. Seeger and Cohen say that they are broadening their repertoire. They have been collecting and performing around the country.
    5:40 Tracy Schwartz talks about Dick [DeVoll] and the next song.
    6:41 "Tom Sherman's Bar Room" [also known as "The streets of Lerado"] Tracy Schwartz, a capella
    9:46 Dildine says that this program is being recorded in the living room of Joe [Bossem] and family. Seeger introduces the next song.
    10:45 "Pretty Little Miss" The NLCR
    14:02 Dildine and John Cohen discuss the previous song. They discuss the next song.
    16:38 "Hawkins Rag" The NLCR (spoons, mandolin and guitar)
    18:05 They discuss the previous song. Dildine and Cohen talk about a song called "The Cuckoo." They talk about change and evolution of traditional songs.
    23:17 "The Cuckoo" John Cohen (banjo, Hobart Smith style)
    23:56 "The cuckoo" John Cohen (banjo, Clarence Ashley style)
    25:59 Dildine and Cohen talk about a film Cohen made of Appalachian mountain singers. It is called "High Lonesome Sound." Seeger introduces the next song. It is a Carter Family song.
    29:28 "Gold Watch and Chain" The NLCR
    32:35 Dildine and Seeger discuss what The NLCR are doing with bluegrass music.
    37:33 "Jaw Bone" or "Old Joe Bone" The NLCR
    39:31 Dildine closes the broadcast.
    39:57 End
  - AFC 1975/001: SR078, Recorded: ca. 1964, RAA 54537; 1:00:54
    This is a recording for a John Dildine (prerecorded) radio broadcast devoted to the old and new recordings of Reverend John Wilkins. All music is by Reverend Wilkins on vocal and guitar, except where noted.
    Start "Railroad Bill, opening theme. Dildine introduces the program and Reverend Robert Wilkins.
    1:12 Reverend Wilkins talks (prerecorded).
    1:40 unidentified blues Wilkins
    5:01 Dildine talks about the previous recording and the following recording.
    5:30 "Do Lord" Wilkins
    9:48 Dildine discusses the previous recording. He introduces an interview he made with Reverend Wilkins on February 18, 1964.
    10:24 Dildine interviews Reverend Wilkins. They talk about recordings he made in the 1930s. Wilkins no longer plays the blues because he has become a Reverend. They talk about his musical history.
    17:27 (Interview continued) They talk about Wilkins moving from blues to "church music." They talk about Wilkins performing outside the context of his church.
    27:04 Dildine does a station break and introduces Dick Spottswood.
    27:45 Dildine and Spottswood talk about: how Spottswood found Reverend Wilkins; recent recordings of Reverend Wilkins and of Mississippi John Hurt; the renewal of interest in blues and old blues musicians; young people playing blues and old time music.
    38:13 "Thank You Jesus" Wilkins, instrumental
    43:13 Dildine does a commercial. He and Spottswood talk about: Reverend Wilkins' new recording being available soon; Reverend Wilkins and John Hurt will be at the Newport Folk Festival this year.
    49:08 "Just a Closer Walk with Thee" Wilkins
    52:23 "Jesus Will Fix It All right" Wilkins
    56:55 Dildine and Spottswood talk about Reverend Wilkins' recordings. Dildine closes the broadcast. "Railroad Bill," closing theme.
    1:54 End
  - AFC 1975/001: SR079, Recorded: unknown, RAA 54538; 1:00:04
    This is a recording for a Dildine radio broadcast of a live interview with Séamus Ennis. It was prerecorded.
    Start "Ned of the Hill" Ennis, pennywhistle
    2:01 Dildine and Emmis talk about how Ennis learned music and became a musician. His father and grandfather were musicians. Ennis describes the pipes he plays. He can't play the bagpipes today because they have suffered from the weather change from Ireland to D.C. Dildine asks him to pay a tune he learned from his grandfather.
    9:25 "The Trip We Took over the Mountain" Ennis, pennywhistle
    11:07 Dildine and Ennis discuss the prior song. Dildine says that Pete Seeger has recorded aversion of the song. They discuss traditional singing in Ireland being a cappella. They talk about the songs Ennis has collected.
    14:40 Ennis tells the story of the next song. He sings it first in Gaelic and then in English, is own translation.
    16:30 unnamed song in Gaelic Ennis, a cappella
    19:00 unnamed song in English Ennis, a capella
    20:22 Dildine and Ennis discuss the previous song. The talk about the music Ennis has collected.
    21:45 "Ned of the Hill" Ennis in English, then in Gaelic, then back to English (all a cappella) and then on the pennywhistle.
    29:30 Dildine does a station break and commercial. They talk about Ennis collecting for the BBC archives.
    34:55 ["The Corn Crake"] Ennis, a cappella
    37:30 Dildine and Ennis talk about when and how Ennis caught a corn crake. They talk about folk songs and folk tales of Scotland and Ireland. Ennis says that the same motifs are found throughout Europe. Ennis tells the tale of a stone mason building a castle.
    47:32 Dildine asks about a song called "Bonnie Bunch of Roses."
    48:42 "Bonnie Bunch of Roses" Ennis, a cappella
    52:54 SE tells where and how he learned the previous song. Dildine and Ennis talk about the continuing of traditional music in Ireland. They talk about Ennis's involvement in Irish television. He does a weekly, 30 minute children's program.
    57:49 Dildine concludes the program.
    58:40 unidentified Ennis, pennywhistle
    1:04 End
  - AFC 1975/001: SR080, Recorded: unknown, RAA 54539; 1:02:34
    This is a recording for a Dildine radio broadcast. It is an interview with Bill Vanaver. It was recorded a few days before the broadcast.
    Start "Railroad Bill," opening theme. Dildine introduce Bill Vanaver and they talk.Vanaver is a college student in anthropology and folklore. The came to folk music at a summer camp he attended.
    4:04 "Little Sadie" Vanaver, vocal and banjo
    6:10 Dildine and Vanaver discuss the previous song. They discuss how Vanaver learns songs. They discuss Vanaver's approach to music. Dildine asks what he is trying to do with his music.
    10:35 "Italian Red Wine" Vanaver, vocal and guitar (a Woody Guthrie song)
    14:37 They discuss the previous song.
    16:14 "Empty pockets Blues" (a Pete Seeger song) Vanaver, guitar and vocal
    19:30 Vanaver says he took some guitar lesson in Philadelphia in 1956. He was influenced by Pete Seeger. He says he came to the instrument before singing. They discuss associating songs with specific people or specific events. They discuss Vanaver as a performer.
    28:13 Dildine does a station break and a commercial.
    29:40 Dildine talks about Vanaver. They talk about Elizabeth Cotten.
    31:10 Freight Train" (an Elizabeth Cotten song) Vanaver, vocal and guitar
    34:35 Dildine and Vanaver discuss the previous song. They discuss the popularization of folk music. Vanaver says the he's listened to many traditional performers. They talk about Pete, Mike and Peggy Seeger as influences on his music. Dildine asks Vanaver what he'd like to do for a career. They discuss the next song. Dildine talks about the Folklore Society of Greater Washington.
    44:50 "From Earth to Heaven" (an Uncle Dave Macon song) Vanaver, vocal and guitar
    47:08 They discuss the previous song.
    48:30 "Paddy on the Turnpike" Vanaver, banjo
    49:44 They discuss songs on "the banjo project." They talk about bagpipes and lap dulcimers. They talk about singing a cappella and singing with instruments.
    49:55 "Blossom" (a Vanaver composition) Vanaver, guitar
    56:32 Dildine asks Vanaver to do another song.
    57:03 medley of banjo tunes Vanaver, banjo
    59:40 Dildine closes the program. "Railroad Bill," closing theme.
    1:02:34 End
  - AFC 1975/001: SR081 (1), Recorded: unknown, RXG 0757; 48:22
    This recording seems to have been made at a party or a "hoot" in a private residence. None of the attendees or performers are identified. This is part 1 of 2. The second part is on SR081 (2).
    Start "The Girl I Left behind Me" male singer with guitar
    3:01 Conversation
    10:05 "Going Down the Road Feeling Bad" group
    11:58 Conversation
    12:38 "Midnight Special" group
    14:45 Conversation
    15:32 "Fireman Save My Child" group
    15:59 Conversation
    16:16 "Pick a Bale of Cotton" group
    17:54 Conversation
    18:48 "Down in the Valley" group
    21:45 Conversation
    23:30 "The Riddle" ("I gave my love a cherry") group
    25:43 Conversation
    26:30 "No John No" group
    28:19 Conversation
    28:50 "Brandy Leave Me Alone" group (sung as a round)
    30:34 Conversation
    31:58 "Streets of Lerado" group (sung normally then as a round)
    34:04 Conversation
    34:58 "Zoom Golly Golly" group (sung as a round)
    35:43 Conversation
    36:28 "Hey Lolly Lolly" group
    42:01 Conversation
    42:34 "Careless Love" group
    43:43 Conversation
    44:17 "The Titanic" ("It was sad when the great ship went down") group
    46:31 "Jesse James" group
    48:22 End
  - AFC 1975/001: SR081 (2), Recorded: unknown, RXG 0757; 46:03
    This recording seems to have been made at a party or a "hoot" in a private residence. Most of the attendees and performers are not identified. This is part 2 of 2. The first part is on SR081 (1).
    Start "Jesse James" group
    0:55 Conversation
    3:03 "Down in the Willow Garden" group
    5:20 "John Hardy" group
    6:58 Conversation
    7:40 "I'm On My Way" group
    11:29 Conversation
    12:12 "Bring Me a Little Water Sylvie" group
    13:08 conversation
    14:08 "Old 97" group
    15:40 Conversation
    17:05 "Henry Lee" Chris and Pixie Christie
    19:50 Conversation
    20:46 My Horses Ain't Hungry" Chris and Pixie Christie
    22:40 Conversation
    23:01 [unable to identify the first line is "When are We Gonna Get Married"] Chris and Pixie Christie
    24:20 Conversation
    25:12 "Raccoon and Possum" unidentified man with banjo
    26:33 Conversation
    26:50 "Poor Little Turtle Dove" unidentified man
    28:32 [unable to identify this song] unidentified man singing
    29:52 Conversation
    30:15 "Around the Corner Beneath the Berry Tree" unidentified woman and group
    32:52 Conversation
    33:33 "That Good Old Mountain Dew" group
    37:40 Conversation
    38:45 "Frankie and Johnny" group
    42:40 Conversation
    43:06 "He Sat Down Beside Her and Smoked His Cigar" women lead the group
    46:03 End
  - AFC 1975/001: SR082, Recorded: 1965-08-02, RXG 0758; 30:52
    This is a recording for a Dildine radio broadcast. His guests are Sandy Paton and Norman Kennedy. This is the second part of the broadcast. The first part is on SR083.
    Start Dildine introduces the broadcast. He says that the previous song (not recorded on SR082) was "Foggy Dew" from the singing of Harry Cox. Paton agrees. Dildine says that Norman Kennedy is from Scotland. Dildine says that this program was recorded in the Green Mountains of Vermont for later broadcast. Dildine does a station break.
    3:20 Dildine talks with Norman Kennedy. Paton talks about a spinning wheel in his home that Kennedy used. Kennedy says that he is also a weaver. Dildine asks how Kennedy learned to speak Gaelic. Kennedy responds. They talk about "mouth music."
    7:24 Several examples of mouth music Kennedy
    9:21 Kennedy says the previous songs were in Gaelic. He discusses them. Dildine asks about "didling." Paton, Kennedy and Dildine discuss this.
    11:33 Several examples of "didling" Kennedy
    13:06 Kennedy discusses the previous songs and the tradition of "didling." Dildine and Kennedy talk about Kennedy's music. Dildine, Paton and Kennedy talk about unaccompanied singing.
    18:28 Dildine asks Kennedy about how bagpipe tunes are transmitted from piper to piper. Kennedy responds.
    20:15 [unidentified song and singing style] Kennedy
    20:50 Kennedy says that the previous songs were pipe tunes. Dildine asks about singing styles influenced by the bagpipe and singing styles influenced by guitar and banjo. Kennedy responds. Paton adds to the conversation. They discuss what Kennedy should sing next.
    26:02 ["My Son David'] Kennedy
    30:03 Dildine concludes the broadcast.
    30:52 End
  - AFC 1975/001: SR083, Recorded: 1965-08-02, RXG 0759; 31:12
    This is a recording for a Dildine radio broadcast. His guests are Sandy Paton and Norman Kennedy. It was recorded in the Green Mountains of Vermont for later broadcast. This is the first part of the broadcast. The second part is on SR082.
    Start Dildine introduces the broadcast. He says that Sandy Paton is involved with Folk Legacy Records and that Norman Kennedy has just done some recording for Folk Legacy.
    0:40 Dildine asks Paton when he first met Kennedy. He responds. Dildine asks Kennedy how it feels to be in the United States. He responds. Dildine asks if he can hear something from Paton and from Kennedy.
    2:39 "Busk, Busk Bonnie Lassie" Kennedy
    4:34 Dildine asks where Kennedy learned the previous song. Kennedy and Dildine discuss this. Kennedy talks about where he learns his songs. He talks about how people respond to his songs. Kennedy talks about learning stories and lore from the old people.
    8:40 The three of the talk about a plant called yarrow and how it is used in old traditional songs. Kennedy talks about how the area around his home in Aberdeen, Scotland is like the hills of Vermont.
    10:20 Dildine asks Paton to do a song. They talk about singers singing to share their music. Paton talks about Folk Legacy Records. They talk about musicians competing rather than sharing their music. Paton discusses the song he is going to sing.
    16:20 [unidentified song; the first line is "I made my way up to the door, a pretty fair maid came o'er the floor"] Paton
    17:45 Kennedy talks about night visit songs.
    19:52 "The Time has Come, I Can No Longer Tarry" Kennedy
    23:16 The three of them discuss night visiting songs. Dildine asks about a song called "Foggy Dew." They discuss this song.
    26:53 "the Foggy Dew" Dildine
  - AFC 1975/001: SR084, Recorded: 1966-02-26, RXG 0760; 20:42
    This is a recording for a Dildine radio broadcast. His guests are Chuck and Nan Perdue. The broadcast continues on SR085.
    Start Dildine introduces the program. He says that it was recorded in his living room. He introduces Chuck Perdue and says the he is the current President of the Folklore Society of Greater Washington (FSGW).
    1:08 Chuck says that he is from Georgia. Nan says that she grew up in Los Angeles and spent her first twelve summers in Texas. They say that they are going to sing a song about radio.
    2:06 "Keep Your Radio On" Chuck and Nan Perdue